Guide to the British-American Tobacco Company Records, 1842-1929
British-American Tobacco Company records 1842-1929
- David Dunlop (Incorporated)
  - Warehouse Storage Books
    - Storage Book for Old St., No. 2, 1911-1912 (Volume 180)
    - Storage Book for Old St., No. 2, 1912 (Volume 181)
    - Storage Book for Old St., No. 3, 1912-1913 (Volume 182)
    - Storage Book for Old St., No. 5, 1913-1914 (Volume 183)
    - Storage Book for Old St., No. 6, 1913-1915 (Volume 184)
    - Storage Book for Old St., 1913 (Volume 185)
    - Storage Book for Old St., Richmond Stemmery, No. 2, 1913-1914 (Volume 186)
    - Storage Book for Old St., Richmond Stemmery, No. 3, 1913-1915 (Volume 187)
    - Storage Book for Picking Room, 1911-1913 (Volume 188)
    - Storage Book for Stemmery, 1911-1912 (Volume 189)
    - Storage Book for Stemmery, 1912-1913 (Volume 190)
    - Storage Book for Stemming Room, 1913-1914 (Volume 191)
    - Storage Book for Out of Town, No. 1, 1910-1914 (Volume 192)
    - Storage Book for Virginia, No. 2, 1912-1913 (Volume 193)
    - Storage Book, 1913-1914 (Volume 194)
- The Camerons
  The Camerons, like the Dunlops, were Scots, and the two families were once connected by marriage as well as being associated in tobacco manufacturing. The Camerons came to Petersburg in the 1840s. There were three brothers (Alexander,; George, and William) and two sisters, one of whom married Robert Dunlop. The brothers obtained positions with David Dunlop, and Alexander Cameron advanced to a partnership. In 1858 they founded the firm of William Cameron & Brother at Petersburg that continued in independent existence until 1903. Their activities expanded to Richmond where they established Alexander Cameron Co. in 1865 and Cameron & Cameron in 1889. These businesses likewise continued to 1903 when all the Cameron companies were absorbed by British-American. A significant part of the Cameron enterprises were the firms that they began establishing in Australia in the 1870s, there eventually being plants at Melbourne, Sydney, Adelaide, and Brisbane. Their trade was strong in Australia, New Zealand, India, South Africa, and other British dependencies. Until the creation of the American Tobacco Co., the combined Cameron properties were probably the largest tobacco manufacturing enterprises operated by Americans. Information about them is in: biographies of Alexander Cameron (1834-1915) in: The National Cyclopaedia of American Biography, VII, 321-322; the Encyclopedia of Virginia Biography, IV, 259-260 (and of George Cameron in the same work, IV, 154-155); and in the New York Times, Feb. 4, 1915, p. 9. See also Joseph Clarke Robert, The Story of Tobacco in America (New York, 1949), p. 131. The Tobacco Collection includes one or more items from the Cameron companies.
  - Cameron & Cameron
    Cameron & Cameron of Richmond manufactured cigars, cigarettes, and smoking tobacco. Seventeen volumes, 1892-1904, are only a small part of the company's set of records, but they include several valuable letterpress books from the last years of its existence. The Letterpress Book, 1897-1900, has correspondence with Alfred I. Hart of Baltimore who went to the Far East and represented the firm in the markets of Hong Kong, China, and Japan, and trade with the Japanese was especially discussed. Foreign Letterpress Books, 1895-1901, concern the export business, and the Agents' Letterpress Books of 1901 and 1903 record dealings with salesmen throughout the U. S. There are no ledgers, but the Trial Balances of 1902 and 1903 are a partial substitute in those two years.
    In Dunlop's General Statements, 1904-1905, are inventories at the end of 1904 for Cameron & Cameron,; Alexander Cameron & Co., and William Cameron & Brother. The Letterpress Book, 1904-1905, for Dunlop and T. C. Williams includes a reference to the sending of Cameron & Cameron's books to British-American's office in New York City (p. 14).
    - Trial Balances, 1902 (Volume 195)
    - Trial Balances, 1903 (Volume 196)
    - Foreign Letterpress Book, 1895 Mar.-1898 Oct. (Volume 197)
    - Foreign Letterpress Book, 1898 Oct.-1901 Dec. (Volume 198)
    - Agents' Letterpress Book, 1901 Feb.-Nov. (Volume 199)
    - Agents' Letterpress Book, 1903 Mar.-Nov. (Volume 200)
    - Letterpress Book for Alfred I. Hart, 1897 Oct.-1900 Nov. (Volume 201)
    - Letterpress Book, 1896 Nov.-1898 Feb. (Volume 202)
    - Sales Book, 1901 Mar.-1903 Jan. (Volume 203)
    - Sales Summary, 1903 (Volume 204)
    - Credit Notes, 1903 May-1904 June (Volume 205)
    - Inventory Book, 1892-1896 (Volume 206)
    - Inventory Book, 1903 July-1904 Jan. (Volume 207)
    - Checkbook, 1894 Feb.-Dec. (Volume 208)
    - Checkbook, 1902 Mar.-Oct. (Volume 209)
    - Checkbook, 1904 Jan.-May (Volume 210)
    - Cashbook, 1901 Jan.-1904 May (Volume 211)
  - William Cameron & Brother
    This single volume is identified with the company by checking the brand names in the book in Connorton's Tobacco Brand Directory of the United States 1899.
    - Lump Book, 1904 (Volume 212)
- T. C. Williams Co.
  The T. C. Williams Co. of Richmond, Va., dates back to the 1850s when it first appears in the city directories as a tobacco manufacturer. It was incorporated in 1889. By 1903 it had become one of the largest tobacco exporters in the U. S., sending abroad nearly five million pounds of chewing tobacco a year and a small amount of smoking tobacco. Williams was a formidable rival of the British in Australia, South Africa, and elsewhere. This rivalry ended in 1903 when British-American bought the export business, which thereafter operated as a subsidiary at Petersburg under the name of T. C. Williams Co. The Continental Tobacco Co. purchased the domestic business that was taken into the American Tobacco Co. in the merger of 1904. Information about the firm is in: the New York Times, April 11, 1903, p. 1, and May 8, 1903, p. 3; the Report of the Commissioner of Corporations on the Tobacco Industry (Washington, 1909); and Joseph Clarke Robert, The Story of Tobacco in America (New York, 1949), p. 130.
  The Tobacco Collection includes one or more advertising items for this company.
  The thirty volumes, 1903-1913, record operations of the firm during its first decade as a subsidiary of British-American. The set of books is very incomplete. Three important volumes are the Cost Sheets for 1903-1904 and 1905-1912 that contain a variety of reports, often monthly, such as trial balances, costs, inventories, transactions, etc. Stock records are numerous, especially those for brands. An inventory of Dec. 31, 1904, is included in Dunlop's General Statements of 1904-1905.
  The company's business records may have been sent to the office in New York; see the reference in Dunlop's Letterpress Book of Jan.- July, 1906 (p. 890).
  - Volumes
    - Letterpress Book, 1903 June-Sept. (Volume 213)
      (The principal formulas for domestic brands that were turned over to the Continental Tobacco Co. are given on pages 1005-1031)
    - Letterpress Book, 1905 Jan.-Feb. (Volume 75)
      (Included in Dunlop's Letterpress Book, 1904 Aug.-Oct. Several Williams' letters are in Dunlop's Letterpress Book, 1906 Jan.-July
    - Journal, 1903-1915 (Volume 213.1)
    - Cost Sheets, 1903 Apr.-1904 Aug. (Volume 214)
      (Statements of shipments to foreign countries are at end of this volume)
    - Cost Sheets, 1905 Aug.-1908 Dec. (Volume 215)
    - Cost Sheets, 1908 Dec.-1912 July (Volume 216)
    - Invoice Book, 1903 Apr.-1904 Sept. (Volume 217)
    - Invoice Book, 1904 Sept.-Oct. (Volume 218)
    - Materials Purchase Register, 1904 Jan.-Aug. (Volume 219)
      (1 p. of 1903 Nov. included)
    - Checkbook, 1904 Aug.-1905 Jan. (Volume 220)
    - Press Room Order Book, 1897 Sept.-1900 May (Volume 221)
      (Some tobacco labels are fastened into this book)
    - Stock of Redried Leaf, 1903-1904 (Volume 222)
    - Leaf Stock Book, 1908-1910 (Volume 223)
    - Stock Book for Cigar Tobacco, 1903-1907 (Volume 224)
    - Brands Stock Book, 1904 (Volume 225)
    - Brands Stock Book, 1904-1905 (Volume 226)
    - Brands Stock Book, 1905-1906 (Volume 227)
    - Brands Stock Book, No. 2, 1905-1906 (Volume 228)
    - Brands Stock Book (A-N), 1906-1907 (Volume 229)
    - Brands Stock Book (O-W), 1906-1907 (Volume 230)
    - Brands Stock Book (A-N), 1907-1908 (Volume 231)
    - Brands Stock Book (O-Z), 1907-1908 (Volume 232)
    - Brands Stock Book (A-N), 1908-1909 (Volume 233)
    - Brands Stock Book (O-Z), 1908-1909 (Volume 234)
    - Brands Stock Book (A-N), 1910 (Volume 235)
    - Brands Stock Book (O-Z), 1910 (Volume 236)
    - Brands Stock Book (A-L), 1911 (Volume 237)
    - Brands Stock Book (M-Z), 1911 (Volume 238)
    - Brands Stock Book (A-M), 1912 (Volume 239)
    - Brands Stock Book (N-Z), 1912 (Volume 240)
    - Brands Stock Book, 1913 (Volume 241)
- British-American Tobacco Company (Petersburg Branch)
  - Journal, No. 8, 1913 June-1915 Sept. (Volume 242)
  - Payroll Book for Lump Room, 1903 Sept.-1904 Sept. (Volume 243)
  - Payroll Book for Lump Room, 1904 Sept.-1905 Aug. (Volume 244)
  - Payroll Book for Stemming Room, 1904 Oct.-Dec. (Volume 245)
  - Brands Stock Book, 1904-1905 (Volume 246)
  - Brands Stock Book, 1905-1906 (Volume 247)
  - Brands Stock Book (A-L), 1906-1907 (Volume 248)
  - Brands Stock Book (M-W), 1906-1907 (Volume 249)
  - Brands Stock Book (A-I), 1907-1908 (Volume 250)
  - Brands Stock Book (M-W), 1907-1908 (Volume 251)
  - Brands Stock Book (A-L), 1908-1909 (Volume 252)
  - Brands Stock Book (M-Z), 1908-1909 (Volume 253)
  - Brands Stock Book (A-L), 1910 (Volume 254)
  - Brands Stock Book (M-Z), 1910 (Volume 255)
  - Brands Stock Book (A-L), 1911 (Volume 256)
  - Brands Stock Book (M-Z), 1911 (Volume 257)
  - Brands Stock Book (M-Z), 1912 (Volume 258)
  - Brands Manufactured and Shipped, 1913 (Volume 259)
- Volumes Combining Accounts of British-American,; T. C. Williams, and David Dunlop Including Some Volumes Not Specifically Labeled.
  - Cost Sheets
    - Cost Sheets, 1904 July-1905 July (Volume 260)
    - Cost Sheets, 1912 July-1915 Aug. (Volume 261)
    - Cost Sheets (Copies received at office in New York City), 1903 Aug.-1908 Dec. (Volume 262)
  - Details of Cost
    These volumes provide cost and inventory figures for the various brands, but not in the detail of the earlier books of David Dunlop.
    - Details of Cost, 1915 (Volume 263)
    - Details of Cost, 1917 (Volume 264)
    - Details of Cost, 1919 (Volume 265)
  - Daily Sales
    Daily sales of the brands of each company with cumulative figures for the month.
    - Daily Sales, 1904 June-Dec. (Volume 266)
    - Daily Sales, 1905 Sept.-Mar. (Volume 267)
    - 268 Daily Sales, 1906 Mar.-Sept. (Volume 1906 Vol.)
    - Daily Sales, 1907 Apr.-Sept. (Volume 269)
    - Daily Sales, 1908 Feb.-July (Volume 270)
    - Daily Sales, 1910 Apr.-June, and 1912 July-Aug. (Volume 271)
    - Daily Sales, 1913 Jan.-May (Volume 272)
    - Daily Sales, 1913 May-Sept. (Volume 273)
    - Daily Sales, 1914 June-Oct. (Volume 274)
    - Daily Sales, 1914 Oct.-1915 Feb. (Volume 275)
    - Daily Sales, 1915 Feb.-July (Volume 276)
    - Daily Sales, 1915 July-Dec. (Volume 277)
    - Daily Sales, 1915 Dec.-1916 June (Volume 278)
    - Daily Sales, 1916 June-Sept. (Volume 279)
    - Daily Sales, 1916 Sept.-1917 Feb. (Volume 280)
    - Daily Sales, 1917 Feb.-June (Volume 281)
    - Daily Sales, 1917 June-Oct. (Volume 282)
    - Daily Sales, 1917 Oct.-1918 May (Volume 283)
    - Daily Sales, 1918 May-Oct. (Volume 284)
    - Invoice Book, 1905 June-Dec. (Volume 285)
    - Invoice Book, 1907 Jan.-1908 Jan. (Volume 286)
      (Includes Dunlop letters of 1906 July-Sept.)
    - Invoice Book, 1908 Jan.-Feb. (Volume 287)
      (Including some Dunlop cost records of 1907 Oct.)
    - Invoice Book, 1909 Nov.-1910 Mar. (Volume 288)
    - Factory Order Sheets, 1915 July-Dec. (Volume 289)
    - Shipping Book, 1902 Nov-1903 Dec. (Volume 58)
    - Shipping Book, 1904 Jan.-Nov. (Volume 290)
    - Shipping Book, 1905 Sept.-1906 Jan. (Volume 291)
    - Shipping Book, 1906 June-Oct. (Volume 292)
    - Shipping Book, 1906 Oct.-1907 Feb. (Volume 293)
    - Shipping Book, 1907 Feb.-June (Volume 294)
    - Shipping Book, 1907 June-Sept. (Volume 295)
    - Shipping Book, 1907 Sept.-Dec. (Volume 296)
    - Shipping Book, 1907 Dec.-1908 Mar. (Volume 297)
    - Shipping Book, 1908 Mar.-June (Volume 298)
    - Shipping Book, 1908 Nov.-1909 Feb. (Volume 299)
    - Shipping Book, 1913 Jan.-1914 Nov. (Volume 300)
    - Petersburg Sales, 1913-1915 (Volume 301)
    - Wrapping Material Stock Book, 1904-1906 (Volume 302)
    - Wrapping Material Stock Book, 1906-1910 (Volume 303)
    - Wrapping Material Stock Book, 1910 (Volume 304)
    - Wrapping Material Stock Book, 1911 (Volume 305)
    - Wrapping Material Stock Book, 1912 (Volume 306)
    - Wrapping Material Stock Book, 1913 (Volume 307)
  - Payroll and Time Books
    These books of wages and hours presumably belonged to the factory at Petersburg that manufactured all the brands of British-American and its subsidiaries. Brand names of the different firms occasionally appear in the volumes. The Time Books have three different formats - apparently for different parts of the operations - and like volumes are listed together. The tables of contents of the two Payroll Ledgers of 1918 list the Leaf Department and Factories No. 1 and No. 2, and the workers in the factories are divided into various categories, some of which are divisions within the plants.
    - Time Book, 1903 Sept.-1904 Sept. (Volume 308)
    - Time Book, 1905 June-1907 Jan. (Volume 309)
    - Time Book, 1908 Dec.-1910 Oct. (Volume 310)
    - Time Book, 1901 Oct.-1905 Oct. (Volume 47)
      (Gap in records: 1904 Aug.-1905 June; records of 1903-1904 are from Old St., Wythe St., and West Hill factories)
    - Time Book, 1906 Apr.-1908 Feb. (Volume 311)
    - Time Book, 1908 Feb.-1909 Dec. (Volume 312)
    - Time Book, 1909 Dec.-1911 July (Volume 313)
    - Payroll Book, 1902 Nov.-1904 Dec. (Volume 314)
    - Payroll Book, 1918 Sept.-Nov. (Volume 315)
    - Payroll Book, 1918 Dec. (Volume 316)
    - Payroll Ledger Factory No. 1, 1918 (Volume 317)
    - Payroll Ledger Factory No. 2, 1918 (Volume 318)
    - Work Sheet Stock Book, 1905-1906 (Volume 319)
    - Work Sheet Stock Book for Fillers, Wrappers, and Casings, 1908-1913 (Volume 320)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Factory, No. 2, 1906-1907 (Volume 321)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Factory, No. 4, 1908-1909 (Volume 322)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Factory, No. 5, 1910 (Volume 323)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Factory, No. 6, 1911 (Volume 324)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Factory, No. 7, 1912 (Volume 325)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Factory, No. 8, 1913 (Volume 326)
    - Leaf Stock Bock for Daily Factory Reports, No. 1, 1905-1906 (Volume 327)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Daily Factory Reports, No. 2, 1906-1907 (Volume 328)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Daily Factory Reports, No. 3, 1907-1908 (Volume 329)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Daily Factory Reports, No. 4, 1909 (Volume 330)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Daily Factory Reports, No. 5, 1910 (Volume 331)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Daily Factory Reports, No. 6, 1911 (Volume 332)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Daily Factory Reports, No. 7, 1912 (Volume 333)
    - Leaf Stock Book for Daily Factory Reports, No. 8, 1913 (Volume 334)
    - Stock Book, 1903 (Volume 335)
    - Stock Book, 1904-1905 (Volume 336)
    - Stock Book, 1916 (Including some entries of 1915 Dec.) (Volume 337)
    - Stock Book, 1917 (Including some records from 1915-1916) (Volume 338)
    - Brands Stock Book, 1903 (Volume 339)
    - Brands Stock Book, No. 1, 1904 (Volume 340)
    - Brands Stock Book, No. 2, 1904 (Volume 341)
    - Casing Stock Book, 1909 (Volume 342)
    - Casing Stock Book, 1910 (Volume 343)
    - Casing Stock Book, 1911 (Volume 344)
    - Casing Stock Book, 1912 (Volume 345)
    - Casing Stock Book, 1913 (Volume 346)
    - Casing Cost and Distribution Stock Book, 1913 (Volume 347)
    - Record of Tobacco Prized, 1903-1904 (Volume 348)
    - Record of Tobacco Prized, 1905-1908 (Volume 349)
    - Record of Tobacco Prized, 1905-1910 (Volume 350)
    - Record of Tobacco Prized, 1906-1911 (Volume 351)
    - Record of Tobacco Prized, 1908-1910 (Volume 352)
    - Record of Hogsheads of Leaf Sent to Warehouses, 1911-1912 (Volume 353)
    - Old St. and Wythe St. Leaf Accounts, 1904-1905 (Volume 354)
    - Record of Dutiable and Taxable Materials Received in and Exported from the Bonded Manufacturing Warehouse, 1906-1909 (Volume 355)
    - Record of Drawback Entries for Granulated Sugar and Nulomoline, 1912-1913 (Volume 356)
- Export Leaf Tobacco Company
  The Export Leaf Tobacco Co. was listed in 1918 and 1924 as a substantial subsidiary of British-American that operated as the latter's tobacco buying agency. It was still listed in 1967 in Moody's Manual of Investments where it was described as a wholly owned subsidiary of the Brown & Williamson Tobacco Corp. that was in turn owned entirely by British-American. Information about Export Leaf Tobacco Co. can be found in: the city directories of Petersburg and Richmond; Reavis Cox, Competition in the American Tobacco Industry, 1911-1932 (New York, 1933 ); and in Nannie May Tilley, The Bright-Tobacco Industry, 1860-1929 (Chapel Hill, 1948).
  Less than a dozen volumes represent the operations of Export Leaf, and it is not always certain what functions the accounts were meant to record or to which department and city they belonged. In 1919 there was a department at Richmond, according to the city directory, and several volumes are labeled Richmond Stemmery, Richmond Storage, and R. S. In the Petersburg directory for 1915-1916 the company was referred to as a tobacco stemmer and repriser, and several volumes are labeled Petersburg Dept. In any case, these books relate more to storage, inventory, and processing than to the firm's activity as a buying agent for British-American.
  There is a large collection of papers of the Export Leaf Tobacco Company at East Carolina University.
  - Petersburg Department
    - Receiving Book, 1914-1915 (Volume 357)
    - Transfer Book, No. 4, 1913 Oct.-Nov. (Volume 358)
    - Wrapper Dept., Picking Results, 1912-1914 (Mostly 1913-1914) (Volume 359)
  - Richmond Stemmery
    - Leaf Used in the Stemming Room, 1913 (Volume 360)
    - Leaf Used in the Stemming Room, 1913-1915 (Volume 361)
    - Leaf Used in the Stemming Room, 1915-1916 (Volume 362)
    - Leaf Used in the Stemming Room, 1916 (Volume 363)
    - Storage Book, 1913 (Volume 364)
    - Storage Book, 1913-1914 (Volume 365)
- Bland Tobacco Company
  The Bland Tobacco Co. of Petersburg, a manufacturer of plug tobacco, appeared in the city directories in the later 1890s. It was dissolved after the American Tobacco Co. purchased its entire capital stock in 1904. Bland was a small factory For its trial balance of early 1905 listed capital stock of only $50,000. The company is noted in the Report of the Commissioner of Corporations on the Tobacco Industry (Washington, 1909), p. 185.
  There are only two volumes for this company, but one of them includes significant information about it.
  - Statements, 1904 Sept.-1905 Jan. (Volume 366)
    (Includes trial balances Monthly cost details, closing entries, sales, expenses, etc.)
  - Checkbook, 1904 June-Dec. (Volume 367)